Guide to the New York World's Fair collection ARC.077
Brooklyn Historical Society
New York World's Fair collection
1936-1940, 1960-1965
Brooklyn Historical Society
ARC.077
6.14 Linear Feet in eleven manuscript boxes, two artifact boxes, and one oversize box.
The New York World's Fair collection includes materials from the 1939 and 1964 World's Fairs. Both took place in Queens, N.Y. at Flushing Meadows Park, a site that was extensively redesigned and landscaped in preparation for the 1939 Fair. The collection contains pre-planning documents, preliminary site reports, maps to the grounds, public relations material, memorabilia, clippings, artifacts, invitations to Fair ceremonies, and individual pavilion guides, among other items.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials on the 1939 New York World's Fair were donated by Lewis N. Anderson, Jr., Wesley Baker, Mrs. James H. Durgin, Herbert S. Hale, and Mrs. Ross Miner, 1966; Millicent Mullineux, 1977; and John B. Shiel, date unknown.
Materials on the 1964 New York World's Fair were largely collected by staff members of the Long Island Historical Society (now the Brooklyn Historical Society) who attended the Fair. A smaller number of items were donated by the New York World's Fair 1964 Corporation, date unknown.
Historical Note
The site for both the 1939 and 1964 World's Fairs was Flushing Meadows Park in Flushing, Queens, N.Y. Extensive work was done before the 1939 Fair to convert the site from its previous existence as a giant ash heap to a suitable park, fairgrounds and exhibition site. Parks Commissioner Robert Moses, who was to play a large role in the 1964 World's Fair plans, was involved in ensuring that the community would get a usable park after the Fair was over.
Despite the Great Depression and instability in Europe, engineer Joseph F. Shagden and Edward F. Roosevelt, cousin to United States President Franklin D. Roosevelt, began to plan in 1935 for a 1939 World's Fair to take place in New York City, its purpose being to "celebrate the 150th anniversary of the inauguration of George Washington and the launching of the new American government under the Constitution." The 1939 theme, "Building the World of Tomorrow," had as its grand architectural symbols an immense white sphere called the Perisphere and a triangular obelisk called the Trylon. A special attraction called "Democracity," illustrating the delights of a city of the future, was also a highlight of the exhibition. The Fair ran from April 30, 1939, to October 31, 1939, and then from May 11, 1940, to October 27, 1940. Dozens of countries participated, building grand pavilions to present their cultures and traditions to all Fair attendees. In addition, scores of businesses presented exhibits showcasing new wares and products, including the American companies General Electric, Consolidated Edison, and the National Broadcasting Corporation. Masterpieces of Renaissance art were also shown in art exhibitions, while the popular "Town of Tomorrow" showed fifteen demonstration homes, each designed to appeal to a different taste.
Decades later, another World's Fair took place on the same site. Parks Commissioner Robert Moses became president of the New York World's Fair Corporation and was instrumental in the pre-planning phases and implementation of improvements to the site. Construction on Shea Stadium (then known as Flushing Meadow Park Municipal Stadium and later demolished in 2009) also began at this time. Moses's interest in the World's Fair site coincided with a decision from the same time period to decline to support construction of a new stadium for the Brooklyn Dodgers.
The 1964 World's Fair ran from April 22, 1964, to October 18, 1964, and then from April 21, 1965, to October 17, 1965. Its theme was "Man in a Shrinking Globe in an Expanding Universe," an idea that seemed appropriate in the newly arrived space age. The architectural symbol of this fair was the Unisphere, which can still be viewed on the former site today. As with the previous fair, country pavilions showcased their cultures and cuisines, and business and industry exhibits showed products and innovations.
Sources:
"Gateway to the World's Fair," New York Herald Tribune, April 30, 1939, pp. 2-6.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Other Finding Aids
An earlier version of this finding aid, containing a detailed folder listing, is available in paper form at the Othmer Library. Please consult library staff for more information.
Scope and Contents
The New York World's Fair collection is composed of eleven manuscript boxes, one oversize flat box, two artifact boxes, and one rolled storage box totaling 6.35 linear feet and covering the periods 1936 to 1940 and 1960 to 1965. The collection has been arranged into three series:
Series 1: 1964 Fair Series 2: 1939 Fair
Series 1 constitutes Boxes 1 and 2, Artifact Box 2, Rolled Storage Box 1, and some items in the oversize box. Items include preliminary reports and planning documents detailing the work to be done on the Fair site in Flushing Meadows Park. The maps and photographs in these reports provide valuable documentation of the extent of the planning and improvements made to the park. The Rolled Storage Box holds a collection of newspaper clippings about the Fair.
Series 2 contains nearly all of the remaining 9 manuscript boxes, Artifact Box 1, and items in the oversize box, and has been divided into 5 subseries: Theatrical and film productions, Exhibitions, Travel guides, Miscellaneous printed material, and Guide books. The subseries Travel guides, consisting of travel brochures to individual American states and to countries around the world, is perhaps the most prominent subseries. The Miscellaneous printed material subseries is also substantial and consists of memorabilia and artifacts such as restaurant menus, invitations to opening day ceremonies, packets of souvenir Fair tickets, and three sticks of Wrigley's chewing gum, along with many more items. Two copies of a 35 mm film reel entitled "Come to the Fair" are also included in Series 1.
Flushing Meadows-Corona Park (New York, N.Y.); Clippings (information artifacts); Brochures; Memorabilia; Pamphlets; Maps; Guidebooks; Advertising |x Tourism; New York (N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Queens (New York, N.Y.); Musicals |z New York (State) |z New York; Reports; Tourism |z South America; Tourism |z United States; Tourism |z Middle East; Tourism |z Oceania; Historical films |z United States; Tourism |z Europe; Travel guidebooks; Souvenirs; Publications; Roads |x Exhibitions; Industries |x Exhibitions; Insurance companies, American |x Exhibitions; Postage stamps |x Exhibitions; Horticulture |x Exhibitions; Food |x Exhibitions; Family life |x Exhibitions; Health |x Exhibitions; Bulletins; Newsletters; Futurism (Architecture) |x Exhibitions; Bylaws (administrative records); Dwellings |x Maintenance and repair |x Exhibitions; Corporations, American |x Exhibitions; Magazines (periodicals); Certificates of incorporation; Artifacts (object genre); Art |x Exhibitions; Office equipment and supplies |x Exhibitions; Railroads |z United States |x Exhibitions; Religion |x Exhibitions; Commencement ceremonies |z New York (State) |z New York; Books; Fairs |z New York (State) |z New York |x Design and construction; New York World's Fair 1964-1965 Corporation; New York World's Fair (1939-1940: New York, N.Y.); Brooklyn Historical Society (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); New York World's Fair (1964-1965: New York, N.Y.); Long Island Historical Society; New York World's Fair 1939-1940 Corporation
- Series 1: 1964 Fair, 1960-1965; in two manuscript boxes, one artifact box, and one oversize box. (Box 1, Box 2, Box Artifacts ARC.077 2 of 2, Oversize ARC.077 OS 1, Box 12)
  Scope and Contents
  This series makes up Boxes 1 and 2, Artifact Box 2, and part of the oversize box. Included are materials on the construction and preparation of the 1964 Fair, pavilion brochures, exhibit pamphlets, official Fair guides, materials concerning the exhibit of the Brooklyn Historical Society (then the Long Island Historical Society) at the Fair, items pertaining to the opening and re-opening ceremonies, a press packet, and various maps and memorabilia. Oversize items include a boxed book chronicling the history of the Vatican (published to coincide with the Vatican's appearance at the Fair), a report on the preparation of the site for the Fair, and a preliminary report on the proposal of the World's Fair, published by the New York World's Fair Corporation, and a photo album containing images of pavillions and visiting diginitaries. Contained in Artifact Box 2 are such items as a plastic lei, three soda cups, a Belgian cookie tin, a cocktail napkin, pins, plastic rings, and an irradiated dime.
- Series 2: 1939 Fair, 1936-1940; in nine manuscript boxes, one artifact box, and one oversize box. (Box Rolled Storage 1, Box Artifacts ARC.077 1 of 2, Oversize ARC.077 OS 1, Reel 2 35mm reels)
  This series, making up the 9 remaining manuscript boxes, Artifact Box 1, and the rest of the oversize box, consists of various brochures, pamphlets, memorabilia, and artifacts from the 1939 Fair. It is divided into five subseries:
  Missing Title
  Theatrical and film productions
  Exhibitions
  Travel guides
  Miscellaneous printed material
  Guide books
  - Subseries 1: Theatrical and film productions, 1939-1940 (Box 3)
    This subseries consists of programs, advertisements, and memorabilia pertaining to various theatrical shows that played at the Fair, including Railroads on Parade, American Jubilee, and The Aquacade. There are also items pertaining to Land of Liberty, a film celebrating American history that was shown at the Fair. Two copies of a 35 mm film reel entitled "Come to the Fair" are also included and are housed separately from the rest of the materials in this series.
  - Subseries 2: Exhibitions, 1939-1940
    This subseries contains catalogs, brochures, and pamphlets from various exhibitions shown at the Fair pertaining to such subjects as art, office supplies, railroads, religion, food, horticulture, health, family life, industry, roads and highways, home improvement, stamps, and insurance companies. Some large corporations represented in this subseries include Consolidated Edison, Ford Motor Company, and the Kodak Company.
    - Art (Box 3)
    - Office buildings (Box 3)
    - Railroad (Box 3)
    - Religious (Box 3)
    - Children's World (Box 3)
    - Food building (Box 3)
    - Horticulture (Box 4)
    - Stamps (Box 4)
    - Highways and Horizons (Box 4)
    - Health (Box 4)
    - Industrial (Box 4)
    - Home improvement (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
    - Insurance companies (Box 5)
    - Kodak (Box 5)
  - Subseries 3: Travel guides, 1939-1940
    This subseries contains travel brochures advocating tourism in countries across the world. The majority of the brochures pertain to several American states and countries throughout Eastern and Western Europe. A smaller number of brochures pertain to Canada, as well as countries in South America, Africa, Asia, the Caribbean, and the Middle East. While most brochures are written in English or contain English translations, a small number are written almost entirely in the their languages of origin, including Spanish, French, and Slovak.
    - Africa - Europe (Eastern) (Box 5)
    - Europe (Western) - Middle East (Box 6)
    - North America: United States: Arizona - Massachusetts (Box 7)
    - North America: United States: Michigan - Vermont (Box 8)
    - North America - South Pacific (Box 9)
  - Subseries 4: Miscellaneous printed material, 1936-1940
    This subseries includes maps, newsletters, bulletins, newspaper clippings, and the certificate of incorporation and by-laws of the New York World's Fair Corporation. Oversize items include an official World's Fair pictorial map, special magazine issues devoted to the Fair from such publications as the New York Herald Tribune and the New York Times, and official souvenir books. This subseries also includes items contained in Artifact Box 1, such as season ticket passes, ticket booklets, stamps, stickers, pins, a paper towel, and three sticks of Wrigley's chewing gum.
    - Maps (Box 9)
    - Inside the Fair (Box 9)
    - World's Fair News (Box 9)
    - World's Fair Bulletin (Box 10)
    - Clippings (Box 10)
    - Ephemera (Box 10)
    - Mixed printed material (Box 11)
  - Subseries 5: Guide books, 1939-1940 (Box 10, Box 11)
    This subseries includes offical World's Fair guide books for 1939 and 1940, as well as tourist guides for both the World's Fair and New York City.